<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mercies memorial: or, Israel's thankful remembrance of God in their high estate, for his mercifull remembring of them in their low estate. In a sermon before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the Right Worshipful the Aldermen, and the Companies of the city London, on the 5th. of November, 1656. / By Ralph Venning.</title>
            <author>Venning, Ralph, 1621?-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E899_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5095</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872794</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872794</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168436</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168436)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 135:E899[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mercies memorial: or, Israel's thankful remembrance of God in their high estate, for his mercifull remembring of them in their low estate. In a sermon before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the Right Worshipful the Aldermen, and the Companies of the city London, on the 5th. of November, 1656. / By Ralph Venning.</title>
                  <author>Venning, Ralph, 1621?-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Rothwell, at the Fountain in Goldsmiths-row in Cheapside.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657. [i.e. 1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 30"; the 7 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXXVI, 23 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Mercy --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168436:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MERCIES MEMORIAL: OR, <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s thankful Remembrance of God in their high eſtate, for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull remembring of them in their low eſtate.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon before the Right Honourable the LORD MAYOR, the Right Worſhipful the ALDERMEN, and the COMPANIES of the City LONDON, on the 5th. of <hi>November,</hi> 1656.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> RALPH VENNING.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. <hi>107.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Oh that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe; and for his wonderful works to the children of men.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> at the Fountain in Goldſmiths-row in Cheapſide. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:168436:2"/>
            <head>TICHBORN Mayor. <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>November,</hi> 1656.</head>
            <p>IT is ordered that Mr. <hi>Venning</hi> be deſired from this Court to Print his late Sermon at <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sadler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168436:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:168436:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168436:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir ROBERT TICHBORN LORD MAYOR, And the Right Worſhipful The ALDERMEN of the City of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable and Honoured,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had received your Order for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this Sermon, I procured the beſt Copy I could, by which and the beſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory I had of what I delivered, I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to preſent it to your view; not without a little addition to ſome heads, which then <hi>I</hi> could not enlarge.</p>
            <p>The reſt of this addreſſe <hi>My Lord and Gentlemen,</hi> is not to complement and flatter you, but earneſtly yet humbly to beſeech you that you would (as <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſaid to <hi>Heſter</hi>) ſeriouſly and ſtudiouſly conſider, wherefore God hath brought you to this high eſtate, hear the place and <hi>(as the Prophet ſaid of the rod)</hi> him that hath
<pb facs="tcp:168436:4"/>appointed it; Be pleaſed to Know and account that <hi>the doing your duty in your Place is the greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your place;</hi> whereas elſe it will be ſaid that your Places honoured you, but you honoured not your Places.</p>
            <p>Indeed 't is the faſhion of this World to ſeek great things for themſelves, 'tis their devotion to ſacrifice to their own nets, 'tis their ambition to Lord it; they are paſſionately enamoured with the Delights and Delicacies of this life, which the <hi>heavenly St. John</hi> calls the luſt of the eye, the luſt of the fleſh and the pride of life; <hi>'Tis all but luſt, and the luſt of the World, which World and which luſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>paſſeth away:</hi> and which the <hi>Wiſe Solomon</hi> on ſad and dear bought experience, calls vanity of vanities and vexation of ſpirit; yet after all theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek. But <hi>ſaith our bleſſed Lord and Saviour,</hi> it ſhall not be ſo with you, you are not your own, and therefore ſhall not ſeek your own, but are Chriſt's; and therefore ſeek the things of Chriſt, and endeavour to doe great things for God: Oh be not led away with <hi>the error and example of this World</hi>'s <hi>admirers,</hi> to be fond of a poor and miſerable becauſe but temporary and periſhing greatneſs. 'Tis <hi>a meer Pageant</hi> which is but a ſhew, and a ſhew that paſſeth away, as you know.</p>
            <p>'Twas <hi>David's</hi> praiſe, and 'twill be yours if you tread in his ſteps, that he ſerved not onely his generation, but the will of God in his generation, <hi>or his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to the will of God:</hi> Conſider then what is the good and perfect and acceptable will of God, that you may be in readineſſe to every good
<pb facs="tcp:168436:4"/>word and work, walking worthy of God to all well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing.</p>
            <p>Indeed <hi>(to ſpeak as the thing is)</hi> you have none to pleaſe, none to ſerve but God; you may not be the ſervants of Men, and you muſt not be the ſervants of Sin; onely ſanctifie the Lord in your hearts, love him, ſerve him, let him be your fear, and your dread; <hi>Fear to diſpleaſe the God you love, and love to pleaſe the God you fear;</hi> leſt you be found <hi>(which God forbid)</hi> among them that had a name to live, but were dead; that had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Chriſt, but practitioners for ſelfe, and for the World.</p>
            <p>If the World frown and accuſe you for <hi>non</hi>-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, let it be to you a ſmall thing <hi>(as it was to the good as well as great Apoſtle)</hi> to be judged by mans day, ſeeing your judgement is with the Lord; and give me leave to tell you, let the World look as big and as ſowre as it can, you may ſafely and honourably avow it; that <hi>the beſt way to pleaſe all,</hi> or diſpleaſe any with leaſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>is to pleaſe him who is all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember with all that you muſt one day give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your <hi>Stewardſhip,</hi> to the great God of Heaven and Earth, who will not judge according to appearance, but he <hi>(ſearching hearts)</hi> will judge righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and give to every man according to his works: Now <hi>I wiſh with my ſoul,</hi> that you may doe ſo well in this your day, as that in that great and terrible day of the Lord, you may hear the joyful ſound, of <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervants,</hi> enter ye into your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters joy.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add no more but my deſire to God for a bleſſing
<pb facs="tcp:168436:5"/>on this Sermon, that as your ears by what you heard, ſo your eyes by what you ſee, may affect your heart to live, <hi>for that is,</hi> to give thanks to God in your high eſtate, who remembred us in our low eſtate.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So prayes, <hi>Right Honourable</hi> And <hi>Right Worſhipful,</hi> Your humble Servant in the ſervice of Chriſt Jeſus <hi>RALPH VENNING.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decemb. <hi>1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168436:5"/>
            <head>MERCIES MEMORIAL: OR, <hi>Iſraels</hi> thankfull remembrance of God in their high eſtate; for his mercifull remembring of them in their low eſtate;</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>From PSAL. 136.23.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Who remembred us in our low eſtate; for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the compleating of the ſenſe, you are to reade it thus, <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord, who remembred us in our low eſtate; for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I preſume it cannot (I am ſure it ought not to) be ſaid of us this day, as it was ſaid of them in <hi>Acts</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> 32. <hi>Some therefore cried one thing, and ſome another; for the aſſembly was confuſed, and the more part knew not wherefore they were come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> Who is ſuch a ſtranger in this our <hi>Engliſh Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> as not to have heard of the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon?</hi> is there either Popiſh enemy, or Proteſtant friend, that knows not what a juſt Right and lawfull Title the <hi>fifth of November</hi> hath to this Obſervation and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168436:6"/>Solemnity? If <hi>David</hi> would not have his ſoul for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <hi>all,</hi> that is, not any of all the benefits of God: much leſs ſuch as have a remark upon them for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſignall and tranſcendent. If Perſonall mercies deſerve their memoriall, ſurely Nationall mercies deſerve a memorable celebration.</p>
            <p>Of this then I may ſay as in the twelfth of <hi>Exod. ver.</hi> 42. only turning night into day, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> into <hi>England, It is a day much to be obſerved unto the Lord, for bringing them out of the Land of Egypt; this is that day of the Lord to be obſerved of all the children of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>in their generations.</hi> But not to Preface away any more of your time in a caſe ſo cleer as this is; not only known by us, but acknowledged by our enemies; we need not ask, <hi>Is there any cauſe?</hi> for they themſelves have confeſt the cauſe.</p>
            <p>This Pſalm may be intitled as the 38 Pſalm is, <hi>A Pſalm to call to remembrance,</hi> only with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that that Pſalm calls miſery, and this Pſalm calls mercy to remembrance; which is ſo much the ſweeter to be remembred.</p>
            <p>It was penned on an occaſion, and to an end like this, for which we are met this day to make a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acknowledgment, and a pious commemoration of the mercies of God to the States of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, the Veſſell in which all our Intereſts were imbarqued. Let us then <hi>give thanks to the Lord, who remembred us in our low eſtate, for his mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words (which may have for Title, <hi>Mercies Memoriall</hi>) you have theſe three generall parts:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Here is their remembring, and an ackcow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168436:6"/>of Gods remembring them, <hi>who remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred us in our low eſtate.</hi> Wherein you may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Mercy it ſelf in this word, <hi>remembred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author of this mercy, in this word, <hi>who;</hi> who is this <hi>who? the Lord</hi> in the firſt Verſe, <hi>the God of Gods</hi> in the ſecond Verſe, <hi>the Lord of Lords</hi> in the third Verſe, <hi>who</hi> remembred us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You have the Objects of this Act, or the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers of this mercy, in this word <hi>us;</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. You have the Seaſon of this mercy, or the time when this God thus remembred this People; and that was, <hi>in their low eſtate;</hi> who remembred us <hi>in our low eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, You have an account here of the true Reaſon and Originall of this Mercy; and that is in theſe words, <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> There is no reaſon to be given for Grace, but Grace; there is no reaſon to be given for Mercy, but Mercy; who remembred us, <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, You have a Duty inferred hereupon; and that is that which <hi>(as I told you before)</hi> is to run in common to every Verſe, <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord,</hi> who remembred us in our low eſtate; for his mercy endureth for ever.</p>
            <p>From this Analyſis, or Reſolution of the words, you have theſe four obſervable Propoſitions:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods own People, a People that are neareſt and deareſt to him, may yet be in a low eſtate; <hi>us in our low eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. God remembers his People in their low eſtate (<hi>quoties premebamur,</hi> as one words it) as often as ever
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168436:7"/>we were low; God remembred us when ever our eſtate was low, or whatever our low eſtate was; God remembred us in our low eſtate; who <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred</hi> us in our low eſtate.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Reaſon why God remembers his People in their low eſtate, is, becauſe his mercy endureth for ever; he remembred us in our low eſtate, <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Gods remembring his People in their low eſtate, lays an obligation upon them to give thanks to the Lord; <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred us in our low eſtate; for his mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever.</p>
            <p>The two firſt of theſe will take up the Doctrinall Diſcourſe; the third of theſe will be the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Diſcourſe; and the laſt, the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the whole. Then we ſhall ſay, <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord,</hi> when we have proved that <hi>he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth us in our low eſtate,</hi> and that becauſe <hi>his mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then is the Method which I ſhall obſerve:</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall open and explain the terms, that we may underſtand this Truth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Prove the truth of the Propoſition, that we may believe it. And</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Apply it, that we may improve it, <hi>which is the mercy of all our mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the explanation of the Contents here, I ſhall propound only two Queſtions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When may a People be ſaid to be <hi>in a low eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What it is for God to <hi>remember</hi> his People in their low eſtate?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168436:7"/>
            <p> Firſt, When may a People be ſaid to be in a low eſtate? Some reade it, <hi>when we were dejected and caſt down;</hi> as if he had ſaid, when we were faithleſs through fear; when we were ſo overwhelmed, that we knew not what to do; when we were hopeleſs, and leaſt of all lookt for help, then God remembred us, and the things we feared came not upon us; God being mercifull to us above all that we could ask or think. But I did not <hi>(nor ſhall)</hi> handle it in this ſenſe; <hi>only let me ſay,</hi> that Gods People are ſometimes in this low eſtate, <hi>low in faith, low in hope,</hi> and yet God remembers them; ſo great is his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and our thankfulneſs ſhould be the more.</p>
            <p>But a People may be ſaid to be in a low eſtate, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 1. Actually; or 2. Potentially. Firſt, <hi>Actually;</hi> and that more generally when they are in affliction and miſery; when they taſte the wormwood and the gall, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> pathetically expreſſes it in his <hi>Lamentations;</hi> when they are in want, when they are low in eſtate; or when, as 'tis ſaid in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.39. they are diminiſhed and (from an high degree, from a wealthy eſtate, they are) <hi>brought low,</hi> through op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, affliction and ſorrow; when a People are under <hi>all,</hi> or <hi>either of theſe,</hi> oppreſſion, affliction, or ſorrow, they may be ſaid to be in a low eſtate.</p>
            <p>But more eſpecially they are ſaid to be low <hi>(with reference to the Text)</hi> when they are in the Enemies hand; <hi>that is,</hi> when they are in the Enemies power; as we may gather from the following Verſe, <hi>who hath redeemed us from our enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you ſhall finde that this is reckoned to be their low eſtate in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.18.19. <hi>The Philiſtines
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168436:8"/>alſo had invaded the cities of the low countrey, and of the ſouth of Judah, and had taken Bethſhemeſh, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jalon, and Gederoth, and Shocho, with the villages there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and Timnah with the villages thereof, Gimzo alſo with the villages thereof, and they dwelt there;</hi> for the Lord brought <hi>Judah</hi> low, <hi>becauſe of Ahaz King of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> The Lord brought <hi>Judah</hi> low, and this was the lowneſs of their condition, that they were in the Enemies hands; their Enemies had dominion over them, and took poſſeſſion of their Poſſeſſions. Thus you have it alſo in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.7, 8. <hi>For they have devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Jacob, and laid waſte his dwelling places;</hi> O remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not againſt us former iniquities; let thy tender mercies ſpeedily prevent us, <hi>for we are brought very low.</hi> This was the lowneſs of their condition, that their Enemies had devoured <hi>Jacob,</hi> and laid waſte his dwelling places. But this was not our caſe through mercy, this was not our low eſtate. Yet again therefore</p>
            <p>Secondly, A People are ſaid to be low <hi>potentially,</hi> when they are in the way to be low; when they are deſigned and deſtinated to a low condition, by the craft and cunning malice of wicked men, who <hi>(wo unto them)</hi> dig deep to hide their counſell from the Lord, and whoſe works are in the dark, <hi>ſaying,</hi> who ſees us? and who knows us? who ſit in the lurking places, ſecretly to murder the innocent; whoſe eyes are privily ſet againſt the poor, who lie in wait ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly as a Lion in his den to catch the poor; as if there were no help in their God, and he were not able to deliver them out of their hand; <hi>thus they plot and deſign a people to an eſtate as low as death;</hi> and upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168436:8"/>this account we are ſaid to be ſlain, though but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be ſlain. In <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36. as it is written, <hi>for thy ſake we are killed all the day long, we are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as ſheep for the ſlaughter.</hi> In this we are low, when we are accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter; ſo that though a People are not <hi>actually</hi> in their Enemies po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, though they are not <hi>actually</hi> in miſery, affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſorrow, yet they are ſaid to be low when they might have been ſo, had not God prevented; to be killed all the day long, when they are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it; <hi>for thy ſake are we killed all the day long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appointed as ſheep for the ſlaughter;</hi> and this was our low eſtate out of which God delivered us, <hi>as we remember this day,</hi> we were accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter, we were killed all the day long in our Enemies account. And this ſhall briefly ſuffice for the ſtate wherein they were, and we were; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred us <hi>in our low eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, What is implied in this, that God <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred</hi> them in their low eſtate; the word is a preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant word, it bears twins thrice told, its big, of a ſixth fold ſenſe, as ſo many degrees of mercy in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To remember,</hi> ſignifies to think upon, <hi>in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to forgetfulneſs; thus the word is rendred, <hi>Gen.</hi> 40.14. ſaith <hi>Joſeph</hi> to the Butler, <hi>think on me;</hi> in the Hebrew 'tis <hi>remember me;</hi> yet <hi>ver.</hi> 23 the Butler did not remember <hi>Joſeph,</hi> but forgat him; <hi>that is,</hi> did not think on him. So it is uſed alſo in <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.1. And God <hi>remembred</hi> Noah, and every living thing. It might have been thought, that when the Ark lay floating on the face of the waters, and ran a drift
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168436:9"/>for an hundred and fifty days, that God had forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Noah</hi> and every living thing: but ſaith the Text, God <hi>remembred Noah,</hi> God did not forget <hi>Noah,</hi> God <hi>thought on</hi> Noah; and in this ſenſe God <hi>remembred</hi> us in our low eſtate, God had us in his thoughts, he had not forgot us, which is <hi>no ſmall mercy not to be forgotten of God;</hi> we may dwell in mans thoughts and not be the better for it, but we cannot be in Gods <hi>remembring thoughts</hi> but we ſhall be the better for it. Therefore</p>
            <p n="2">2. To remember <hi>(as the ſecond degree of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy)</hi> ſignifies to take notice of a thing, in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to neglect; ſo it is uſed in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Remember</hi> to keep holy the Sabbath day, take notice, <hi>that is,</hi> neglect it not, <hi>remember</hi> to keep holy the Sabbath day; ſo God <hi>remembred</hi> us in our low eſtate; how? why he did not barely think upon us, but he did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and take notice of us, and conſidered what our caſe was. But</p>
            <p n="3">3. It ſignifies <hi>(as the third degree of mercy)</hi> to lay to heart, to pity and compaſſionate perſons in ſuch a caſe; what am I the better for any bodies thinking of me, if he do not take notice of me, ſo as to pity me in my low eſtate? ſo God doth, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20. Is Ephraim my dear ſon, is he a pleaſant childe? for ſince I ſpake againſt him, <hi>I do earneſtly remember him ſtill;</hi> or, as the Hebrew reads it, <hi>remembring I will remember him;</hi> therefore my bowels are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for him, <hi>I will ſurely have mercy upon him,</hi> ſaith the Lord; this earneſt remembrance was the earneſt of the mercy. But again,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>To remember,</hi> ſignifies yet more <hi>(as the fourth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168436:9"/>degree of mercy)</hi> to be well pleaſed with a perſon in ſuch a caſe, to accept of a perſon in ſuch a caſe; ſo the word is uſed in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.3. The Lord <hi>remember</hi> all thy Offerings, and accept thy burnt Sacrifice; remember, that is, accept; why now thus God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred us in our low eſtate; we were acceptable to him, and well pleaſing in his eye at that time, when by our Enemies we were appointed as ſheep for the ſlaughter; ſo you may ſee it in <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. And when <hi>Cornelius</hi> looked on the Angel, he was afraid, and ſaid, What is it Lord? and he ſaid unto him, Thy prayers and thine alms are come up <hi>for a memoriall</hi> before God; <hi>that is,</hi> they are as a ſweet ſmelling ſavour, as a ſacrifice well pleaſing to God. Thus did the Lord <hi>remember</hi> us; that is, he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of us, he took pleaſure in us, in our low eſtate. But again,</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>To remember,</hi> ſignifies <hi>(as the fifth degree of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy)</hi> to hear, and to grant a requeſt; ſo it is uſed 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.19, 20. And they roſe up in the morning early, and worſhipped before the Lord, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and came to their houſe, to <hi>Ramah,</hi> and <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanah</hi> knew <hi>Hannah</hi> his wife, and <hi>the Lord remembred her;</hi> wherefore it came to paſs, when the time was come about, after <hi>Hannah</hi> had conceived, that ſhe bare a ſon, and called his name <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſaying, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have asked him of the Lord, <hi>God remembred Hannah;</hi> and the next word is, <hi>he gave her what ſhe asked.</hi> So here God remembred us; how? what only think of us, or take notice of us? or did he lay it to heart, and pity and compaſſionate us, and was well pleaſed with us? no, <hi>not only ſo;</hi> but God did
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168436:10"/>hear and grant the deſires and prayers of his people; thus God remembred us. But again,</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>To remember,</hi> ſignifies <hi>(as the ſixth degree of mercy)</hi> to help and ſuccour, or to redeem and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from that which we were appointed to, <hi>from the low eſtate;</hi> and ſo it is in <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.10. Only they would that we ſhould <hi>remember</hi> the poor, the ſame which I alſo was forward to do; remembring of the poor is not barely a thought, but a relieving thought; therefore ſaith he <hi>in the following verſe,</hi> who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us from our enemies; this was the <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of God, <hi>redemption</hi> from enemies. When <hi>Paul</hi> was, <hi>if not forgotten, yet</hi> forſaken of all, then God <hi>remembred</hi> him, and ſtood by him; ſo that though ſentence of death were paſſed, yet God <hi>delivered</hi> from ſo great a death. Now then you ſee what it is for God <hi>to remember</hi> a people in their low eſtate; <hi>it is to think upon them,</hi> in oppoſition to forgetfulneſs; <hi>it is to take notice of them,</hi> in oppoſition to neglect; <hi>it is to lay</hi> their caſe and eſtate <hi>to heart, to pity and compaſſionate them, and to be well pleaſed with them, to hear and to grant their requeſts, to help and ſuccour, to redeem and deliver them from the hand of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now for the proof of this point, that this is a truth, That God remembers, <hi>and thus remembers</hi> his people in their low eſtate; there are ſome truths ſo cleer, that the naming of them is ſufficient evidence for them; as they ſay of ſome errors, they are ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable and groſs, that to repeat them, is to refute them: ſo ſome truths are ſo cleer, that but to name them, is to cleer them, <hi>eſpecially</hi> when it is ſuch a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168436:10"/>truth as experience muſt ſpeak to, as here it is; <hi>who remembred us in our low eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed to which of the Saints ſhall we turn? who can ſay of all the Sons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that God hath forgotten them? did not God <hi>remember Joſeph</hi> in his low eſtate? did not God <hi>remember Iſrael</hi> in their low eſtate? and did not God <hi>remember David</hi> in his low eſtate? Nay, to ſpeak of all at once, did not God <hi>remember Chriſt</hi> in his low eſtate? and this day ſpeaks for us, that God <hi>hath remembred us</hi> in our low eſtate.</p>
            <p>And indeed my beloved, we may take up that Song, and ſing it, in the 124 Pſalm, <hi>If it had not been the Lord, who was on our ſide,</hi> now may <hi>England</hi> ſay, <hi>If it had not been the Lord, who was on our ſide when men roſe up againſt us,</hi> then they had ſwallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled againſt us, then the waters had overwhelmed us, the ſtream had gone over our Soul, then the proud waters had gone over our ſoul; <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord,</hi> who hath not given us as a prey to their teeth; our ſoul is eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as a bird out of the ſnare of the fowlers; the ſnare is broken and we are eſcaped; <hi>our help is in the Name of the Lord,</hi> who made heaven and earth.</p>
            <p>This may we ſay, thus may we ſing, <hi>Is it not ſo?</hi> is there a contradiction to be made againſt this truth? Nay, <hi>my beloved,</hi> the caſe was this, that if God had not been on our ſide, we had been ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up quick; and our not being ſo, ſhews God on our ſide, that God <hi>remembred us</hi> in our low eſtate.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore proceed to the third thing, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168436:11"/>is, <hi>the reaſon why</hi> God remembreth his people in their low eſtate; <hi>that is,</hi> as in the Text, <hi>for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endures for ever;</hi> he harps only on this ſtring, he reckons up a long Catalogue of many mercies; and the reaſon of all theſe is mercy, <hi>only mercy;</hi> the reaſon of one is the reaſon of all, <hi>as I told you before,</hi> there is no reaſon for mercy, but mercy; no reaſon for grace, but grace; who is gracious; <hi>why?</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will, and to whom he will be gracious; ſo that you ſee that <hi>mercy in God, is all the reaſon of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from God to man in his low eſtate;</hi> it is <hi>not</hi> mans me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>but</hi> Gods mercy, it is <hi>not</hi> mans due, <hi>but</hi> Gods gift; it is <hi>not</hi> mans demand (nor was it in this caſe mans deſire) <hi>but</hi> Gods grant; who many times an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers before they call, and when they are yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he is hearing; it was <hi>not</hi> mans meaſure, but Gods allowance; it was <hi>not</hi> after the manner of men, <hi>who uſe to go over where the ſtile is low;</hi> this was <hi>not</hi> becauſe man could make God a requitall, <hi>but</hi> becauſe God would act like himſelf; it was <hi>not</hi> Gods profit, <hi>but</hi> mans neceſſity; it was <hi>not</hi> that God needed man, <hi>but</hi> man needed God; therefore <hi>grace ſtill is as free after it is received, as it was before it was given;</hi> it was not deſerved, and cannot be requited; God therefore gave, as looking for nothing again; <hi>that is,</hi> nothing that can requite it; and you ſhall have for this a double witneſs, <hi>God ſpeaks it, and Saints ſpeak it,</hi> that God ſhews not mercy to man becauſe man pleaſeth him, but becauſe mercy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him; indeed one end that God hath in ſhewing mercy, is, that man ſhould pleaſe him; but that is not the main motive; for in truth to put mans will
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168436:11"/>before Gods, is <hi>ſuch an hyſteron proteron,</hi> that (if I may uſe ſo homely an expreſſion in ſo ſolemn a caſe) I ſay it is <hi>to put the cart before the horſe.</hi> You ſhall finde God ſpeaking, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.21, 22, 23. But I had pity <hi>for my holy Name,</hi> which the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had profaned among the Heathen, whither they went. <hi>Therefore</hi> ſay unto the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord God, <hi>I do not this for your ſakes,</hi> O houſe of Iſrael, <hi>but for mine holy names ſake,</hi> which ye have profaned among the Heathen, whither ye went; And I will ſanctifie <hi>my great Name,</hi> which was profaned among the Heathen, which ye have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned in the midſt of them, and the Heathen ſhall know that I am the Lord, <hi>ſaith the Lord God,</hi> when I ſhall be ſanctified in you before their eyes. <hi>It is a fulſom Doctrine to fleſh and blood, to think it muſt be beholding for all to grace;</hi> ſhame and confuſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to man, mercy belongs to God; man makes work for ſhame and for ſorrow; God works mercy as never obliged to it, but for his holy Names ſake; and <hi>Jeremiah in his Lamentations</hi> makes this acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, and ſo confirms the witneſs of God in <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.21, 22. This I recall to my minde, therefore have I hope; <hi>it is of the Lords mercies</hi> that we are not conſumed, <hi>becauſe his compaſſions fail not.</hi> If it be of the <hi>Lords mercies</hi> that we are not conſumed and brought to utter deſolation, <hi>ſurely then</hi> that we are remembred and delivered <hi>is for no other reaſon,</hi> but becauſe his compaſſions fail not, but his mercy endureth for ever. Thus I have given you the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall part, with what brevity I could; I come now to the Application.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:168436:12"/>
            <p> Firſt then, it will afford us an <hi>information.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Some exhortations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Information is this:</p>
            <p>Doth God remember his people in their low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate? O happy (<hi>how happy</hi>) are they then that are the People of this God! <hi>that have the Lord for their God;</hi> it is not every man in generall that is thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred: no, <hi>God hath his peculiars, for whom he hath his peculiar favours;</hi> indeed his mercy is over all his works; he is good, and doth good to all, but <hi>there is a ſpecialty</hi> to the houſhold of faith; and God that doth command us to do good to all, but <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> to the houſhold of faith, <hi>he doth but command us that which he patterns us;</hi> therefore <hi>David</hi> makes his Prayer in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.4, 5. Remember me, O Lord, with <hi>the favour</hi> that thou beareſt unto <hi>thy people;</hi> O viſit me with thy ſalvation, that I may ſee <hi>the good of thy choſen,</hi> that I may rejoyce in <hi>the gladneſs of thy Nation,</hi> that I may <hi>glory with thine inheritance;</hi> O Lord favour me with the favours, &amp;c. <hi>The good of Gods choſen is a choice good;</hi> and ſo he goes on, O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me with the favours wherewith thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreſt <hi>thy people.</hi> It is an expreſſion in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.5. Happy is he that hath <hi>the God of Jacob</hi> for his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord <hi>his God.</hi> Why the God of <hi>Jacob?</hi> becauſe God, though he be every bodies God, and God of the whole Earth, yet <hi>he is Jacobs God in a more peculiar manner;</hi> he is the God of all the World, by the opening of his hands, and filling them with ſuch bleſſings; and <hi>he is Jacobs God by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening his heart,</hi> and filling him with thoſe bleſſings; and ſo far as heart is above hand, ſo far are heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercies
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168436:12"/>above hand-mercies, <hi>and ſo far are Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more happy then other people. David</hi> hath a ſaying in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. <hi>ver. ult.</hi> Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe; yea, <hi>happy is that people whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> Happy is that people whoſe God is the Lord; there were perſons named before, <hi>who were ſo vain as to ſay,</hi> happy were the people that were in ſuch a caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that had their Barns full, and their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles full, and their Purſes full in the World: I but ſaith <hi>David, Happy is the people that hath the Lord for their God;</hi> if a man had all the World, and had not the Lord for his God, he is leſs happy then he that hath the Lord for his God, and not at all of the World. God alwaies remembers his, <hi>either to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them from evil, or to turn their evil into good;</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſupply them with the things they want, or to let them know that it is good for them that they ſhould want it. <hi>My beloved,</hi> methinks this ſhould engage all of you to look after having God for your God; it is a commendation that paſſeth among you, when: you ſee young men entring on the ſtage of the World, you ſay he is like to do well, <hi>for he minds the main chance,</hi> he takes care to look after his Shop and his Trade, and you ſay ſuch a one is like to thrive. If ever you mean to thrive, to go from a low to an high eſtate, from a poor to a rich eſtate, from a miſerable to an happy condition, look after this, <hi>the having God for your God;</hi> what is God to you if he be not your God? <hi>Tolle meum &amp; tolle Deum,</hi> as he ſaid; 'tis cold comfort to me while I live, and when I die, that there is a God, but (alas!) not my God. You ſee then that nothing concerns you ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168436:13"/>much as this; <hi>nay indeed,</hi> to ſpeak as properly as poſitively, nothing but this, <hi>this is your only inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and this only.</hi> O what an ingagement ſhould this be to every perſon living, to go to the Father by the Son? <hi>for this is the main chance, the one thing neceſſary,</hi> that ye might have a portion with the Son and the Father. <hi>Beloved,</hi> who would not live in Gods thoughts? who would not have God to take notice of them? who would not have God to lay their cauſe to heart, to pity and compaſſionate them? who would not have God to be well pleaſed with them? who would not have God to hear and grant their requeſts? who would not have God to help and ſuccour them, to redeem and deliver them? <hi>O who would not be the Lords people?</hi> it is the ſumme of all the Covenant, I will make with them a new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people;</hi> O what a ſad caſe are they in, that come not under the new Covenant! whatever good we have from communion, it flows from union; <hi>all that comes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly to us, it all comes from this, that God is our God;</hi> therefore I beſeech you to minde this more, look after an intereſt in God. O what will you do in your low eſtate elſe? in your evil daies elſe? when death and ſickneſs ſhall bring you low, what will you do if God be not your God? if you have not a God to think of you, a God to take notice of you, a God to lay to heart, and to pity and compaſſionate you, and a God to grant your requeſts, and to deliver and redeem you, what will you do? O therefore I beſeech you to look after this, to have God for your God; for they, <hi>they only</hi> are happy, and they are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168436:13"/>thrice happy, yea <hi>ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quater<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> beati,</hi> altogether and alwaies, in all eſtates happy, who have the Lord for their God: But for the exhortations, and that thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Doth God remember his people in their low eſtate? let us <hi>truſt God then, when we meet with future ſtraits;</hi> our God is a God that we ſhall need for ever; and why do not we record the years of the right- hand of the moſt high? and the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things that God hath wrought for us, in ages paſt? that the God that hath been our help, may be our hope. Are any of you in a low condition? do any of you that are the Lords people fear, you may be brought low, in any condition whatſoever? <hi>O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this,</hi> God remembers his People in their low eſtate, <hi>and heretofore-mercies are grounds to look for hereafter-mercies;</hi> mercies paſt are grounds to look for mercies to come, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. who delivered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver, <hi>in whom we truſt,</hi> that he will yet delive rus. <hi>O my beloved,</hi> read over your experiences, look over Gods dealings with you, and remember how God dealt with you in ſuch and ſuch and the other low eſtate; and then raiſe up your hopes, ſurely that God that did, the ſame God will remember me in my low eſtate. Why? <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> Gods ſtock is not ſpent, his riches are unſearchable, there is no fathoming of his goodneſſe. If <hi>David</hi> thought <hi>the experience of others a good ground to build his hope and expectation upon,</hi> as he pleads it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.4, 5. Our fathers truſted in thee, they truſted and thou didſt deliver them; they cryed unto thee and were delivered, they truſted in thee and were not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168436:14"/>confounded. <hi>Much more his own experience,</hi> as he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10, 11. thou art he that took me out of the womb, thou didſt make me hope when I hung on my mothers breſts; I was caſt upon thee from the womb, thou wert my God from my mothers belly; <hi>and he adds as if he had ſaid, therefore,</hi> be not far from me now trouble (<hi>new trouble</hi>) is near: and this was ſo ſucceſſeful, that before the Pſalm is ended he praiſeth and calls on others to praiſe God; <hi>for ſaith he</hi> v. 24. God hath not deſpiſed nor abhor red the affliction of the afflicted, but when he cryed unto him he heard.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Be like God;</hi> doth God remember his people in their low eſtate? be like God then, <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them that are in a low eſtate.</hi> Godlineſs what is it, but godlikeneſs; what is it to be godly, but to be like a God? <hi>the life of godlineſs is called in the Scripture, the life of God,</hi> not in this reſpect only, that we have this life from God, or in this, that we live this life to God, but in this, <hi>that 'tis ſuch a life as God lives. God</hi> lives the life of love, and God lives the life of mercy; and ſhall not we now be like God, to live a life of love, and a life of mercy, and good works? <hi>you may pleaſe to obſerve,</hi> that we cannot be in any thing ſaid to be more like God, then in this of mercy; <hi>his Name</hi> when it is proclaimed, what is it, but <hi>the Lord gracious and merciful;</hi> now when are we like God? but when gracious, and merciful. When we are exhorted to be perfect, as our heavenly father is perfect, it is <hi>as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Evangeliſt hath it,</hi> to be merciful as our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father is merciful. And ſo when <hi>Moſes Exod.</hi> 33.16. asked God to ſhew him <hi>his glory,</hi> ſaith God, I will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168436:14"/>cauſe all my <hi>goodneſs,</hi> that is my glory, that is my Name wherein I glory, to paſs before thee.</p>
            <p>You have been honourable, and why ſhould I not hope you will be honourable ſtill in good works? there are poor Children here before your eyes, that call upon you ſaying, <hi>Remember us in our low eſtate;</hi> there are many Hoſpitals that call for this, <hi>remember us in our low eſtate.</hi> And mark I beſeech you what hath the name of pure Religion (and what hath the name, hath the nature of it) <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Pure Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and undefiled before God, and the Father, <hi>is this,</hi> to viſit the fatherleſs and widows in their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and to keep himſelf <hi>unſpotted from the World;</hi> this is the great ſpot of the World, that it is a cruel World, a World without bowels of pitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion; a World that remembers not them that are in a low eſtate: <hi>Mercy is the Churches Grace, and the Churches Glory;</hi> and therefore I beſeech you that you will remember as occaſion offers, and when you are going out of theſe doors, forget not theſe words, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the poor.</hi> There is <hi>nothing more unbecomming a people that have received mercy, then to be hard hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> not to have bowels of mercie, it is to put a blot on our own enjoyments, and to be wanting to that which we proclaim with joy and triumph this day. Oh love and pitie them that are in a low eſtate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that you <hi>your ſelves were ſometimes low,</hi> ſuch were ſome of you. <hi>Thou ſhalt</hi> ſaith God, Deut. 10.19. <hi>Love the ſtranger, for you were ſtrangers in the houſe of Egypt, and ye know the heart of a ſtranger,</hi> Exod. 23.9. You have had experience what a ſad and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate heart attends a low eſtate; <hi>let therefore</hi> the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168436:15"/>brother of a low degree rejoyce that he is exalted, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.9. <hi>yet ſo</hi> as to condiſcend to men of low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16. <hi>we ſeldome forget</hi> God or man in our high eſtate, but it may be ſaid, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.22. in all thine abominations <hi>thou haſt not remembred</hi> the daies of thy youth, when thou waſt naked and bare, in <hi>a low eſtate.</hi> It was the brand that <hi>Gallio</hi> lay under when the Saints were perſecuted, that he cared not for theſe things. O it is a ſad brand <hi>a very black cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> when it may be ſaid of men that they do not care for theſe things. But again,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Doth God remember his people in their low eſtate? O then <hi>let his People remember him in their high eſtate;</hi> he hath ſet you on high, O now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him in your high eſtate: <hi>it is but equal,</hi> that if God remember us when we are low, that we ſhould remember God when we are high; <hi>To ſin againſt the deliverances of God, and a God of deliverance too, is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iniquity;</hi> and yet it is mans great vanity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs, that he is ſeldome more apt to forget God at any time then then when he hath moſt cauſe to remember him; when he hath mercy before his eye, yet then to forget a God; ſee this, Deut. 32.15. <hi>Of the rock that begat thee thou art unmindful, and haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten God that formed thee.</hi> This was the ſin of <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> he grew fat, how? why God fed him <hi>not with courſe fare, not with brown bread and water, but with dainties,</hi> he fed him with Butter of Kine, and Milk of Sheep, with fat of Lambs and Rams of the breed of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> with Goats, and with the fat of the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys of Wheat, and for his drink he had the pure blood of the grape; <hi>and what then?</hi> why then he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168436:15"/>kicked, and forſook the God that made him. God fed him, and <hi>then</hi> he forſook him. <hi>O ſtrange!</hi> One would think that <hi>then</hi> he ſhould have rememberd him; I but he then forſook God, &amp; lightly eſteemed the rock of his Salvation; and ſo you ſhall ſee <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.6. It is there laid to the charge of <hi>Ephraim, ſaith he,</hi> they were filled, and as they were filled, their hearts were exalted; <hi>therefore</hi> they have forgotten me; alas! <hi>therefore they forgot;</hi> what becauſe God filled them? no, but yet then they were exalted, and <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they forgot God</hi> who filled their hand with good and their bellies with his hid treaſure. My beloved you ſee, <hi>Times of enjoyment, though moſt deſirable to us, are moſt dangerous to us;</hi> times of fulneſs, though moſt pleaſing to us, are too too often made by us moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God; that that ſhould be the day of all daies, is ſtrange; therefore we have an exhortation given us, Deut. 6.10, 11, 12. <hi>And it ſhall be when the Lord thy God ſhall have brought thee into the Land, which he ſware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Iſaac, and to Jacob, to give thee great and goodly Cities,</hi> which thou buildedſt not, <hi>and houſes full of all things,</hi> which thou filledſt not, <hi>and wells digged,</hi> which thou diggedſt not, <hi>vineyards, and Olive trees,</hi> which thou plantedſt not; when thou ſhalt have eaten, and be full, <hi>then beware leſt thou forget the Lord,</hi> which brought thee forth out of the Land of Egypt, from the houſe of bondage; <hi>there is not ſuch another time of danger as the full time.</hi> Hence it was that <hi>holy Job</hi> was jealous of his children leſt <hi>they were evil in a good day,</hi> leſt at the time of fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting they ſhould curſe God. Man ſeldom turns his back more upon God then when he hath the greateſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168436:16"/>obligations even before his eyes to keep him cloſe to God; O therefore remember this that <hi>mercies are not given onely for us to uſe to our comfort, but they are given for us to improve for Gods glory.</hi> The Greaks have two expreſſions to ſet out riches by, the one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things had, or things in poſſeſſion, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things uſed; or things improved: now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they account the beſt, which is things uſed, <hi>it is the improvement of mercy, that makes mercy a mercy indeed.</hi> Hath God delivered us out of the hands of our enemies, that we ſhould commit abomination? no, but that we ſhould ſerve him with holineſſe all the daies of our lives; <hi>if not,</hi> what can we expect, but that he ſhould take away our mercies from us, and remember us no more. O therefore take heed that you do not (while you are eating, and drinking in remembrance of God) that you do not forget God. It is but too common, that eating and drinking takes away mens ſtomachs as to ſpiritual things. Tis very ſad that mercies which are given us to indear God to us, <hi>that we might love him the more, and ſerve him the better,</hi> ſhould be ſo abuſed by us as to love him the leſs and ſerve him the worſe; that we ſhould take the corn and the wine and the oyle, the ſilver and gold which God gives us, and prepare them for <hi>Baal,</hi> as they did <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.8. and they <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16, 17-21. But now what will you have us to doe? you will ſay. Why</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Take notice</hi> not onely of the mercies of God, but <hi>of God in the mercies;</hi> not only of the deliverance, but of God in the deliverance; for a deliverance is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ſweet as when the ſoul taſts God in it; <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168436:16"/>are never ſo ſavory as when they ſavour of a Saviour;</hi> ſtudy then not only the mercy, but the God of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>This did Jacob</hi> when his brother <hi>Eſau</hi> asked him Whoſe are all theſe? why ſaith he, <hi>the Children that the Lord hath graciouſly given thy ſervant,</hi> Gen. 33.5. mark it, not only children, or children which God hath given, but children which God hath <hi>graciouſly</hi> given. And ſo <hi>Samuel</hi> you find him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12. not only taking notice of the mercy, but of God in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>hitherto the Lord hath helped;</hi> to have the help without God, is to have help without a bleſſing; and they that do not ſee God in it, they have but half-mercy, they have but the body of mercy; to taſt God in it, and to enjoy God in it, that is the mercy of the mercy. So that in <hi>Num.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 23. Surely there is no inchantment againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> neither is there any divination againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> according to this time, it ſhall be ſaid of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what hath God wrought? <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall not ſay, loe what is wrought, but what hath God wrought; 'tis the Lords doeing and therefore marvellous in our eyes: we ſhall not look upon mercy as marvellous ſweet and precious, unleſs we ſee it is the Lords doing. <hi>God</hi> remembred us ſaith <hi>David.</hi> But again,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Do not onely take notice of God in mercy, but as <hi>David</hi> doth here, <hi>keep catalogues of the mercies of God;</hi> Gods mercies are not to be forgotten; you will remember the kindneſſes of your friend, all his favours and tokens; you will keep your Books of account wherein all your debts ſhall be entered, that they may be remembred, and <hi>ſhall God be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten?</hi> Memory is a ſlippery thing, and many times
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168436:17"/>lets go quickly; therefore did God command <hi>Iſrael</hi> to write down their deliverances; <hi>they had not onely a table for Commands, but a table for Salvations alſo; for</hi> that that is written will abide, <hi>littera ſcripta manet;</hi> and records brings that to mind which elſe would not be thought upon by us, as <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> was remembred by <hi>Ahaſuerus.</hi> God hath a Book of remembrance written for what you do, <hi>and will not you have a Book of remembrance</hi> written for what he doth? God hath it upon record, you have not a good thought, but God writes it down; you ſhed not a tear, but God bottles it up; you make not a prayer, but God puts it in his Book of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance; now ſhall God do ſo for you (not that God hath a weak memory, but it is for your conſolation) and will not you write down his mercies? You know you dare not truſt your memories for your debters, or your debts; <hi>O my beloved,</hi> will you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit every thing to Book but Gods dealings? you can by your Book tell how much ſuch a one owes you, and that ſuch a one is ſo much in your debt, ſuch a time ſo much, and ſuch a time ſo much; but can you doe ſo by Gods dealings to you, that ſuch a time, ſuch a deliverance, and ſuch a time, ſuch a remarkable mercy? Oh let a Book of remembrance be written. But again,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Lay to heart the mercy of God.</hi> If it be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in a book, and not in the heart, it will have but little impreſſion; and therefore 'tis commanded in the Scripture, Deut. 4.9. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelf and keep thy ſoul diligently, leaſt thou forget the things which thine eyes have ſeen;</hi> and (mark this) <hi>leaſt they depart from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168436:17"/>thine</hi> heart; as if he had ſaid, <hi>let not thine heart forget;</hi> as if the beſt memorie lay in the heart; therefore ſaith he, let not thy heart forget; <hi>the ſenſe of mercy is the beſt memory.</hi> I and beloved let me tell you this, <hi>mercy then works ſweetly, when it works inwardly;</hi> when it doth not onely affect the eye and the ear, but the heart. Moreover, you will not be able to give glory to God, if you lay not mercies to heart, Mal. 2. v. 2. <hi>If ye will not hear, and ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my Name, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> I will even ſend a curſe upon you, and I will curſe your bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; yea, I have curſed them already, <hi>becauſe you do not lay it to heart;</hi> all elſe will be nothing, if you do not lay it to heart; you cannot give glory to God. But again,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Give thanks unto the Lord,</hi> who remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred us in our low eſtate, this the very Text calls upon us for; and let the redeemed of the Lord <hi>ſay and do ſo,</hi> whom he hath redeemed from the hand of the enemy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.2. You may pleaſe to obſerve that in Scripture God hath theſe three Titles, <hi>the Hope of Iſrael, the Saviour of Iſrael, and the Glory of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:</hi> pray who was your Hope? was not God? who was your Saviour? was not God? pray then who ſhall be your Glory? ſhall not God? If we have had our mercies from God, ſhall not God have our thanks? The ſtreames in this World, the rivers of Water do all pay their tribute to the Fountain; <hi>they come from the Sea, and thither they go again:</hi> All the world teacheth us to be true tributaries to God; doth not all come from God? by the ſame reaſon all ought to go to him; for ſaith the Text, <hi>of whom, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168436:18"/>to whom</hi> are all things; <hi>de facto,</hi> all is of him, and <hi>de jure,</hi> all ought to be to him.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Let me beſeech you to <hi>give him the the calves of your lips;</hi> let your glory awake, and give glory to God; the tongue of man is called his glory; my heart is glad, and my glory rejoyceth, ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſal.</hi> 16.9. And ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Acts</hi> 2.26. my heart is glad, and my tongue rejoyceth; that which <hi>David</hi> calls glory, <hi>Peter (from the Septuagint.)</hi> calls tongue. So in many places, the tongue of man is called his glory, and wherein? in nothing but in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying God; in any thing elſe, it is his ſhame, but in this that it ſpeaks to the praiſe of God, 'tis the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of man, if man at any time ſay to God, open my lips, my mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy praiſe; and this is required from us in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. By him therefore <hi>let us offer the ſacrifice of praiſe to God continually,</hi> that is, <hi>the fruit of our lips,</hi> giving thanks to his Name; <hi>God doth not think the fruits of our lips ſmall things.</hi> Why haſt thou a tongue, but to ſpeak to the praiſe of God? why haſt thou lips, but to give fruit to God? And then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Give thanks to God by the fruit of you lives;</hi> the calves of your lips if they go alone, are poor pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing calves; <hi>thanks living is the beſt thanksgiving that can be;</hi> therefore you ſhall find in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15, 16. By him therefore let us offer the ſacrifice of praiſe to God continually, that is, the fruit of our lips, giving thanks to his Name; <hi>and is that all? is that enough? Oh no,</hi> But to doe good, and to communicate, forget not; for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed; <hi>as much as to ſay,</hi> the fruit of the lips, without the fruit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168436:18"/>of the hand, and of the life, it is nothing. Pray re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it this day, and for ever; <hi>herein</hi> ſaith Chriſt <hi>is my father glorified, when you bring forth much fruit;</hi> a little fruit ſerves not to give glory to God; herein is my father glorified, when you bring forth much fruit; <hi>a little is as none,</hi> my father is glorified when you bring forth much. And ſo Phil. 1.11. <hi>Be ye filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe which are</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt <hi>unto the glory and praiſe of God;</hi> obſerve it, not onely <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>fruit</hi> of righteouſneſs; but <hi>fruits</hi> of righteouſneſs, and filled with them too; ſo that you ſee it is not a little that will doe it.</p>
            <p>Pray remember this, that your good works may ſo ſhine before men, that you that doe them, may glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God alſo; <hi>by your lips he hath but ſingle, but by your works he hath double glory;</hi> for you that doe them glorifie God, and they that ſee them done will glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God; O therefor give a glorious example. But let me add a few things more, I beſeech you, that your obedience may be qualified towards God, as your mercy hath been qualified from God towards you; how that is, I will tell you preſently; onely this of the preſent mercy.</p>
            <p>It was a preventing mercy; <hi>to be prevented with the bleſſing of good, is the greateſt kind of mercy:</hi> deliverance from evil, is good; but to be delivered ſo, as not to be in evil, is much more good. Who will not reckon it a greater mercy alwaies to be in health, then to be delivered from ſickneſs? though both are mercies, in this mercy we know not a myſterie, in others we have; this is not like peace, the joyful daughter of a ſorrowful mother; this is not like health after a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168436:19"/>but this prevents all theſe; ſo much the greater mercy: <hi>it took away no good from us, it brought no evil upon us;</hi> and how great was this mercy? If this mercy had not been, for ought that I know, many of us had not had a being; or elſe which is worſe, a being not worth the having.</p>
            <p>But now to the qualifications of your obedience. The firſt qualification of your mercy was this, it was <hi>free mercy,</hi> it came not upon conſtraint, it was not forc't, nor wreſted out of the hands of God; freely you have received, freely give; God loves to give cheerfully, and the ſame God loves a cheerful giver.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Your mercy was <hi>according to your own heart,</hi> every way grateful and acceptable to you: let your obedience be ſo to God; be like <hi>David</hi> men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods own heart.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It was ſeaſonable mercy, it was in our low eſtate, it was when you knew not what to doe; for you knew not the danger you were in: So let your obedience be ſeaſonable, then 'tis beautiful.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It was a <hi>ſignal mercy; digitus Dethic,</hi> the finger of God was here, the enemy being judge; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mercies call for ſignal obedience; therefore be you ſure to doe ſome ſingular and ſignal things for God, to return to the Lord <hi>according</hi> to the benefits received. Oh ſay, What? <hi>What anſwerable thing</hi> ſhall I return the Lord for all his benefits? But again,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is <hi>a continued mercy;</hi> we enjoy our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from that mercy to this day; it is not one mercy, and not more, but a chain of mercy; not the mercy of a day, or a year, but the mercy of Ages: <hi>well then,</hi> let us be continual in obedience, let us be Chriſtians,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168436:19"/>not for a day, or for a fit, but Chriſtians throughout every day in the year; not onely Chriſtians here at Church, but at home in the Cloſet, and in the ſhop. And then again Laſtly,</p>
            <p>Sixthly, We have ſuperadded to this <hi>multitudes of other mercies,</hi> heap upon heap, <hi>he loadeth us with his benefits every day;</hi> yea many a time, many a time <hi>we may now ſay,</hi> hath he ſaved us, he is the God of all our Salvations and his mercy endureth for ever; Let us then multiply obedience, and be alwaies abounding in the work of the Lord; Shall mercies encreaſe, and obedience decreaſe? God forbid.</p>
            <p>Take a few provoking conſiderations, and I have done. I might draw conſiderations from <hi>the Author</hi> of the mercy, <hi>God;</hi> a God that was offended by us, a God that needed us not, and a God that gaines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by us; and yet this God remembred us in our low eſtate; that ſhould engage us. I might alſo draw obligations from <hi>the Objects,</hi> and that is <hi>us</hi> that were not only an undeſerving, but an ill-deſerving, and are not a ſuteable returning People. I might draw Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments from <hi>the mercy,</hi> that God <hi>remembred</hi> us in all the ſenſes ſpoken of before; and I might draw argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from <hi>the ſeaſon,</hi> in our low eſtate, and from <hi>the excellency of the duty</hi> of thanksgiving, 'tis a comely thing; it makes us like the Angels whoſe whole em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment and liturgy is to give and live praiſe to God. And <hi>from this alſo</hi> I might enlarge the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the obligation, <hi>that his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> But onely take theſe four Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is dangerous ſinning after mercy received;</hi> and the greater the mercy, the more danger in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; the greater the mercy hath been, the greater
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168436:20"/>the danger of ſinning will be: God was angry with <hi>Solomon</hi> that he turned his heart from the Lord God of Iſrael; I <hi>but what was it that heightned this?</hi> why it was this, that God had appeared to him twice. So ſaith <hi>Ezra,</hi> ſhall we again ſin after ſuch a mercy as this? <hi>ſuch a deliverance as this?</hi> What could we then expect but that God ſhould be angry with us till he had conſumed us, and there ſhould be no remnant nor eſcaping? <hi>Ezra.</hi> 9.14. O ſin no more, leaſt a worſe thing come unto us, God knows how to fetch all his pennyworths out of us; he hath Plagues yet ſeven times more in ſtore; if he give them vent, Woe to us. See <hi>Judges</hi> 10.11, 14. And the Lord ſaid unto the Children of Iſrael, <hi>did not I deliver you</hi> from the Egyptians, and from the Amorites, from the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Ammon, and from the Philiſtins? <hi>yet ye have forſaken me,</hi> and ſerved other Gods; <hi>Wherefore I will deliver you no more:</hi> go and cry unto the gods which you have choſen, let them ſave you in the time of your tribulation; O this, <hi>this is a ſad caſe,</hi> I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you no more. If we forſake God, and forget God after ſuch remarkable Salvation, let me tell you that we incur this, that God ſhould ſay, I will deliver you no more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Our Mercies,</hi> unleſs we make this anſwerable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to God, our mercies <hi>are not compleat;</hi> our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are long a compleating: a mercy is never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat to us till we have returned the glory of it to God; mercies are not perfect mercies, till praiſes are perfect praiſes: See that in the 40 Pſalm and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Mark the ſteps of the mercy. (1) <hi>He inclin'd,</hi> (2) <hi>He heard my cry.</hi> (3) <hi>He brought me up out of an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible pit out of the miery clay.</hi> (4) <hi>Set my feet on a rock.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:168436:20"/>(5) <hi>Eſtabliſht my going; and</hi> 6. As the crown of all, <hi>He put a new ſong into my mouth, Praiſe unto our God.</hi> The mercy was not compleat, though he was ſet on a Rock, <hi>one would think paſt danger;</hi> no, that is not enough that he was ſet upon a Rock, or that he was brought up out of an horrible pit, and out of the Miercy clay, and had his goings eſtabliſhed; <hi>but there is this to make it up compleat,</hi> he hath put a new ſong into my mouth, even Praiſe to our God. <hi>O my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> may it not be feared that you and I have many imperfect mercies? Why? becauſe our returns are ſo imperfect, we do not ſing the new Song, with ſuch life and vigour as we ought to doe. O let us then look about us; our mercies are not perfect or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat till we make an anſwerable return to God for mercies received.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Remember this, <hi>this is all you can do for God,</hi> and this is leſs then God hath done for you: you are not leſs then the leaſt of mercies only before you have them <hi>as to matter of merit,</hi> but leſſe then the leaſt of mercies after you have received them <hi>in reſpect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns;</hi> you can never give God enough, your beſt is too bad, and your All is too little; when you have done all, you are unprofitable ſervants, becauſe you have done but what was your duty to doe; for man is bound to ſerve God with the utmoſt of his Soul and ſtrength; <hi>his all is Gods due;</hi> Man muſt therefore be an unprofitable ſervant; <hi>but O then how unprofitable is man that doth not doe his duty at all!</hi> O my beloved let us do all that we can; for when we haoe done all, it is no more but what we ought, we give God but his own: Yet again,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Remember this, if this be not done, <hi>this day is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168436:21"/>in vain,</hi> and this day is loſt; ſhall we beloved reward evil to our own ſouls, and turn our holy daies and holy duties into iniquity, the day is loſt, it is gone. Saith God concerning the Faſts, <hi>is this the faſt</hi> that I have choſen, for a man to hang down his head for a day? No, no, this is not it. So may God ſay, <hi>is this the Feaſt</hi> which I have choſen? What onely to make a pompous ſhow, and have a Sermon to ſerve for State, is this it? Do you think <hi>beloved,</hi> that God cares for mans Complements? What is it to give God a parcel of good words, and a parcel of bad works? What is it in words to confeſs him, and in works to deny him? What is this? Is this the way of Pra ſe? No, it is Hypocrifie, and the way to undoe all that we doe. I will but borrow the expreſſion of the Pſalmiſt, and ſo conclude, Pſal. 50.16. But <hi>unto the Wicked</hi> ſaith God, <hi>what haſt thou to doe</hi> to decare mine Ordinances, that thou ſhouldeſt take my Covenant in thy mouth? what Wicked? and yet declare my Statutes! What wicked? and take my Covenant! What haſt thou to doe? ah what haſt thou to doe? Conſider this ye that forget God, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you.</p>
            <p>But now if ye offer praiſe by a right ordered Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaion, <hi>What then?</hi> why then ſaith God, Know aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, that <hi>he who offereth praiſe honoureth me, and to him that ordereth his Converſation aright will I ſhow the Salvation of God.</hi> Oh then I beſeech you in the bowels of Chriſt Jeſus, as you tender the honour of God and your own Salvation, that you thus <hi>give thanks to the Lord who remembred us in our low eſtate, for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
